A Finding Aid to the Henry Kirke Brown Papers, 1836-1893, in the Archives of American Art
Archives of American Art
Henry Kirke Brown papers
1836-1893
Archives of American Art
Brown, Henry Kirke, 1814-1886
AAA.browhenr
Archival Resource Key
1 Linear foot
The papers of sculptor and portrait painter Henry Kirke Brown measure 1 linear feet and date from 1836 to 1893. The collection includes Brown's correspondence with his wife, Lydia Louise Udall, his nephew, Henry Kirke Bush-Brown, and other family members. Also included are letters from artists George Catlin, George Fuller, Sanford R. Gifford, James Reid Lambdin, Louis Lang, Erastus Dow Palmer, Hiram Powers, Horatio Stone, and others; five news clippings; and miscellaneous notes.
Arrangement
Due to the small size of this collection the papers are arranged as one series.
Biographical / Historical
Henry Kirke Brown (1814-1886) was an American sculptor and portrait painter born in Leyden, Massachusetts and died in Newburgh, New York.
Conditions Governing Access
Use of original papers requires an appointment and is limited to the Archives' Washington, D.C., Research Center.
Existence and Location of Copies
This collection is available on 35 mm microfilm reels 2770 and 2771 at the Archives of American Art offices and through interlibrary loan. Researchers should note that the arrangement of the material described in the container inventory does not reflect the arrangement of the collection on microfilm.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Henry Kirke Brown papers were donated to the Archives of American in 1981 by Dorothy Young, who acquired the papers from her husband, an art dealer.
Scope and Contents
The papers of sculptor and portrait painter Henry Kirke Brown measure 1 linear feet and date from 1836 to 1893. The collection includes Brown's correspondence with his wife, Lydia Louise Udall, his nephew, Henry Kirke Bush-Brown, and other family members. Also included are letters from artists George Catlin, George Fuller, Sanford R. Gifford, James Reid Lambdin, Louis Lang, Erastus Dow Palmer, Hiram Powers, Horatio Stone, and others; five news clippings; and miscellaneous notes.
Brown's lengthy letters to his wife reveal his devotion to her and the conflict he felt between his art and his personal life. He discusses his work, including progress on his statue of George Washington, located in Union Square, New York City. Letters to his family from Rome and Florence allude to his awe of Italy's monuments. Also included are letters from Washington, D.C. during Brown's tenure as a member of the U.S. Art Commission in the 1860s.
Portrait painters -- Massachusetts; Sculptors -- Massachusetts; Sculpture, Modern--19th century; Italy -- description and travel; Bush-Brown, Henry Kirke, 1857-1935; Catlin, George, 1796-1872; Fuller, George, 1822-1884; Gifford, Sanford Robinson, 1823-1880; Lambdin, James Reid, 1807-1889; Lang, Louis, 1814-1893; Palmer, Erastus Dow, 1817-1904; Powers, Hiram, 1805-1873; Stone, Horatio, 1808-1875; Udall, Lydia Louise; United States.. Art Commission
- Henry Kirke Brown Papers, 1836-1893; Series 1; Archival Resource Key; 0.8 Linear feet Boxes 1-2
  Scope and Contents
  The collection includes Brown's correspondence with his wife, Lydia Louise Udall, his nephew, Henry Kirke Bush-Brown, and other family members. Also included are letters from artists George Catlin, George Fuller, Sanford R. Gifford, James Reid Lambdin, Louis Lang, Erastus Dow Palmer, Hiram Powers, Horatio Stone, and others; five news clippings; and miscellaneous notes.
  Brown's lengthy letters to his wife reveal his devotion to her and the conflict he felt between his art and his personal life. He discusses his work, including progress on his statue of George Washington, located in Union Square, New York City. Letters to his family from Rome and Florence allude to his awe of Italy's monuments. Also included are letters from Washington, D.C. during Brown's tenure as a member of the U.S. Art Commission in the 1860s.
  - Correspondence, 1836; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1837; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1838; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1839; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1840; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 5-8)
  - Correspondence, 1841-1842; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 9-10)
  - Correspondence, 1843; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1844; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1845; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1846; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Correspondence, 1848-1849; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1850; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Correspondence, 1851; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Correspondence, 1852-1853; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Correspondence, 1854; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Correspondence, 1855; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Correspondence, 1856; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Correspondence, 1857; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Correspondence, 1858; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 23-25)
  - Correspondence, 1859-1861; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Correspondence, 1862; Archival Resource Key (Box 1, Folder 27-37)
  - Correspondence, 1862-1863; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 1-5)
  - Correspondence, 1864-1865; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 1866-1869; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 7-10)
  - Correspondence, 1870; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1871; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 1872-1873; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1874; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 14-21)
  - Correspondence, 1875; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 22-24)
  - Correspondence, 1876; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 25-26)
  - Correspondence, 1877; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 27-28)
  - Correspondence, 1878-1882; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 29-33)
  - Correspondence, 1883-1893; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Clippings, 1862; undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 35-36)
  - Miscellaneous, undated; Archival Resource Key (Box 2, Folder 37)